Guide to the Collective: Unconscious Archive MSS.225
Fales Library and Special Collections
Collective: Unconscious Archive
1994-2007
Fales Library and Special Collections
Collective:Unconscious
MSS.225
18 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
Founded in 1995, Collective: Unconscious (C:U) was an experimental theater group strongly committed to the neighborhood of Manhattan's Lower East Side and its developing artists. Collective: Unconscious members staged dozens of their own productions at the group's home on Ludlow Street (and later on Church Street) and rented space to many other performers. As leaders of other performance groups, Collective members also involved Collective: Unconscious in many of the downtown cultural festivals of the 1990s and early 2000s, including the New York International Fringe Festival and the Downtown Arts Festival. The materials in the collection document the production and promotion of performances staged and hosted by the Collective and contains exhaustive documentation of the group's administrative functions and financial difficulties.
Scope and Content note
The Collective: Unconscious archive reflects the experimental theatre group's devotion to theatrical eccentricity, performative creativity, and the downtown Manhattan arts scene. Canvassing the time between the group's inception in 1995 and its subsequent closure in 2008, the archive covers fourteen years of Collective: Unconscious' activities within New York City's theatre movement and documents Collective: Unconscious' contributions to late 20th-century and early 21st-century Manhattan avant-gardism. These activities included the group's production of original in-house plays, its participation in various metropolitan cultural festivals, and its cross-promotion of downtown theatrical groups and events. The archives' contents range from financial documents and administrative papers to experimental stage props.
Provenance
Material within the Collective: Unconscious Archive was donated by the organization to the Fales Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
Collective: Unconscious was founded in 1995 as a confederation of artists working in visual and performing arts. For most of its existence, the group was housed in a space at 145 Ludlow Street on Manhattan's Lower East Side, where it staged its own productions and provided rental space for performances by other emerging artists. Their "big in-house kickoff" in October 1995, Cucho Tailor, was designed to create a "collaborative performance environment". Other significant performances included American Slave Code (2000) by David Pilot and Al Ramos and Charlie Victor Romeo by Bob Berger, Patrick Daniels, and Irving Gregory, as well as several episodic serial plays, such as the 1996-1997 Manifestations and The Lung of Ling (years undocumented). Among the most well-known works mounted by outside artists were Reverend Jen's Anti-Slam and the Robert Beck Memorial Cinema.
In addition to being known for experimental work using a variety of genres and material, often in the service of humor or social critique, Collective: Unconscious also had a reputation for self-promoting and participating in the artistic community of the Lower East Side and downtown Manhattan through other group performances and festivals. Collective: Unconscious members were also the artistic directors of several ongoing performance groups, including the Play Practice workshop, Collective Unconscious Sub-Group Network 23, Collective Unconscious Sub-Group IFAM, and Tribeca Lab Theater. Collective: Unconscious artists participated in The New York International Fringe Festival and the Downtown Arts Festival. The Collective: Unconscious facility also hosted several festivals, including the New York Fringe Festival, the Downtown Arts Festival, and the New York Lower East Side Film Festival.
In 2005, because of increased rental costs, the group was forced to move into a space at 279 Church Street in Manhattan and in 2007-2008, Collective: Unconscious lost its lease and relinquished its rental space altogether. Though not currently active, the group maintains a presence online through their official web site, www.weird.org, which includes promotions for underground zero, an annual festival of experimental theater begun in 2007, to be held at P.S. 122 in the East Village. The archive reflects the group's commitment to a non-hierarchical operating structure—no record of staff titles or distinction between collective members and collective founders will be found. Periodical sources included in the collection mention Caterina Bartha and Daniel Green as being among the group's co-founders. Other members have included Julia Berger, Robert Berger, Audrey Crabtree, Patrick Daniels, Justin Davila, Gecko, Irving Gregory, Christiaan Koop, Scott Kravet, Jaimie Mereness, Al Ramos, Kelly Schornak, and Steve Zacks.
References:
1. Collective: Unconscious, company history and mission statement included in press kit, undated. 2. Collective: Unconscious web site, www.weird.org.
Arrangement
For the most part, materials are arranged chronologically. Undated materials may be found at the end of each Series or Subseries. Video and audio media have been divided into subseries to differentiate production recordings from commercial or other recordings. Each media element has been assigned a unique identification number and, for the most part, has been arranged alphabetically by production title.
The collection is arranged into seven series:
Series I: Production Files
Series II: Administrative Files
Series III: Photographic Material
Series IV: Realia
Series V: Video
Series VI: Audio
Series VII: Computer Disks
The Oversize section includes oversized material from: Series I, Subseries A, B; Series III; and Series IV.
Missing Title
Series I: Production Files
Series II: Administrative Files
Series III: Photographic Material
Series IV: Realia
Series V: Video
Series VI: Audio
Series VII: Computer Disks
Oversize
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Floppy disks.; Festivals.; Negatives (photographic); Videocassettes.; blueprints (reprographic copies); Props (object genres); Posters.; Financial records; Art |x Finance |z United States; Administrative records.; Mini-DV.; Audiocassettes.; VHS; Off Off-Broadway theater.; Experimental theater -- New York (State) -- New York.; Experimental theater; Fliers (printed matter); Photocopies.; Slides (photographs); Photographs.
- Series I: Production Files
  Scope and Content note
  Series I: Production Files is comprised of paper archives that relate to Collective: Unconscious's production of theatrical events. This series includes scripts for individual plays and festivals, proposals, publicity, and miscellaneous papers associated with the general production of artistic forms and materials relating to the rental of performance space. Also included are near-comprehensive show reports documenting the date, title, attendance and ticket price of various performances. The material has been arranged within four subseries:
  Subseries A: General
  Subseries B: Programs, Press, and Promotional
  Subseries C: Scripts
  Subseries D: Publications/Source Material
  - Subseries A: General
    - Mission statements and history, N/A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Production guidelines and signed waivers, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Submissions and Proposals, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Production reports and schedules, Jan-Feb 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Production reports and schedules, Apr-May 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Production reports and schedules, June-July 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Production reports and schedules, Aug-Oct 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Production reports and schedules, Oct-Dec 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Pilot & Aviation Logbook" - audience register for Charlie Victor Romeo, [1999] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Drama Desk Award Nominations - Charlie Victor Romeo, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Actors' Equity Association rules and agreement, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fringe Festival, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Fringe Festival, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Museum of Experience files, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Resumes and letters of interest, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Mermaid Parade, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Production reports and schedules, Mar-Apr 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Production reports and schedules, May-June 2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Production reports and schedules, Jun-Aug 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Production reports and schedules, Sep-Oct 2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Production reports and schedules, Nov-Dec 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Whispers Now, The Revolution" notebook, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Manhattan Neighborhood Network Guide, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Production reports and schedules, Jan-Feb 2001 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Production reports and schedules, Mar-Apr 2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Production reports and schedules, May-Aug 2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Production reports and schedules, Sep-Dec 2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Howl! Festival of East Village Arts, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Production reports and schedules, Jan-Mar 2002 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Production reports and schedules, Feb-Mar 2002 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Production reports and schedules, Apr-May 2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Production reports and schedules, May-July 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Production reports and schedules, Jul-Aug 2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Production reports and schedules, Sep-Oct 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Production reports and schedule, Nov-Dec 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Production reports and schedules, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Production reports and schedules, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Production reports and schedules, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Production reports and schedules, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Anthology Film Archives program, Jan-Mar 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Misc. programs, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Production reports [blank], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Audition Schedule, March 26, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Open Mic schedule, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Annotated paper nameplates, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Saynayas storyboards, 5-98 (diagrams), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Manifestations audience surveys, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [sheets with typewritten phrases], undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Misc. production outlines, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Misc. production drawings and diagrams, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Rev. Jen's Anti-Slam schedule, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - VAC Plastics and Winland Electronics catologs, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Newspaper clipping - Balthus, "De gitaarles", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Subseries B: Programs, Press, and Promotional
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Misc. Press, 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Misc. Press, 1996-2002 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Press releases, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Advertising rates and Time Out New York Media Kit, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - The Battle Cry [C:U publication], April 2000 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Membership info, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Film projects info, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Fringe Festival publications/programs, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Charlie Victor Romeo promo, programs, and press releases, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Charlie Victor Romeo press, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 5th Annual Mr. Lower East Side Pageant ballots, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - 145 Ludlow St. closing announcement, Nov 30, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Press, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Flyers, programs, and calendars, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - C:U comic strips, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Misc. flyers, programs, and calendars, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Misc. flyers, programs, and calendars, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Misc. flyers, programs, and calendars, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - IFAM "Project Tentacle #1" info and press releases, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Robert Beck Memorial Theatre promo and flyer scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fax cover sheets for press, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: Scripts
    - What About Me, by Nicolas Arjona, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - gas/house bang/gang, by Benj Gerdes, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - The Saynayas Project, IFAM, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - American Slave Code, by David Pilot, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Schizorampant Before Extinction Series, by Katherine Chronis, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Kidnap Girl, by Nick Colt, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Good Morning Justin, by Dan Krumm, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Whispers Now, The Revolution, by William Pleasant, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Crying Out Loud, by Lennie Varvarides, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Dali! Inside the Mind of a Genius, by William Lee, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Dali! Inside the Mind of a Genius, by William Lee (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Safe Harbor Amsterdam, by Jack Luceno, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Search For My Inner Latina, by Michele Carlo, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Aircraft accident reports/transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Beyond the Comfort Zone, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Bier of the Bleeding Homonculus, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Bush Death [abbreviated version for Mermaid Parade], undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Charlie Victor Romeo, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Christmastime in the City, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - For Arrested Protesters Everywhere, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Hot Property, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Love Research, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - The Lung of Ling [misc. episodes], undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - The Lung of Ling [misc. episodes], undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Macky Does September, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Macky Dees sheet music, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Manifestations: The Numinous Hand [serial play], undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Manifestations: War is Cold [serial play], undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Monster Robot Versus Giant Tentacle, IFAM, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Never Too Late, by Sumner Arthur Long, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Nikola Tesla [proposal and outline of stageplay], by Mike Olshan, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Roof Party, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Special Guest, by Donald Elser, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Squabbles, by Marshall Karp, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Subterranean Homesick Blues, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Toolbox, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Partial/incomplete scripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Subseries D: Publications/Source Material
    - Misc. comic books, 1958-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Cyclops no.2 (London: Aug 1970) (Box 4, Folder 2)
      General
      Publication removed and catalogued in the Downtown Collection within Fales
    - Fortean Times: The Journal of Strange Phenomena no. 74 (Apr/May 94); no. 77 (Oct/Nov 94), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Crazy Christian Conspiracy Comics no. 3 (July 96) [Church of the SubGenius], 1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - WAR: White Aryan Resistance (Nov 97; Feb 98), 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Abracadabra magic catalog, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Crappucino Vol. 1, Issue 2, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Stark Fist of Removal [the official newsletter of the Church of the SubGenius], 1999 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Abrahadabra (Technologie) Nr. 13, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Continental Airlines safety instructions, 737-500, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Cyberjihad (Drencrom Presents) Year 0, Issue 1 [Church of the Subgenius], undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Did Rudy Giuliani Kill 300 Firemen on 9/11?" pamphlet, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Foreign language primer, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - The Paranoid Times, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Saddam Hussein [foreign language] comic book, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series II: Administrative Files
  Series II: Administrative Files includes documents relating to building maintenance, day-to-day operations and communication. Extensive billing records and itemized receipts from multiple operating years are also included. This series also contains meeting minutes, financial records, tax returns and grant paperwork. Among the financial records are copies of the group's leases and lengthy correspondence with both landlords and attorneys over issues and disputes. Of particular interest are folders relevant to the lease and to insurance, which document the increasing cost of rental and fire insurance in a Lower East Side neighborhood in a state of rapid change after 9/11. The material has been divided into three subseries:
  Subseries B: Minutes
  Subseries C: Financial
  - Subseries A: General
    - 279 Church St., Dept. of Buildings Certificates of Occupancy, 1991-2000 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Brian Homa personal, 1994-2000 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Closed.
    - Lease & landlord files - 145 Ludlow St., 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Alliance of Resident Theatres - Directory, Services Guide, Fiscal Year 96-97 survey, and other misc. files, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Lease & landlord files - 145 Ludlow St., 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence - postcards, 1997-2001 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Weekly planning calendar, March-July, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Grant files, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Alliance of Resident Theatres - membership info, newsletters, 2001 fiscal analysis, and other misc. files, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Lease & landlord files - 145 Ludlow St., 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Donation solicitations [from other organizations], 2000 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence - to Reverend Jen, from Christopher, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Central Contractor Registration - Defense Logistics Agency [for Robert Berger], 2000 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Visual AIDS fundraising, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Parental consent forms [Talent Unlimited High School], 2000 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Gift Matching Matching Program files, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Liability Insurance files, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Liability Insurance files, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Lower East Side Business Association - misc. files, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 279 Church St. - Certificate of Occupancy, New York City Department of Buildings, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Materials For The Arts (MFTA) - membership/registration files, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 279 Church St. - Chapin Loan info, renovation, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - NY State Liquor Authority License, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 279 Church St. building/theater - misc legal, financial, and logistical files, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - 279 Church St. - lease changes and notations, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - 279 Church St. - Rider lease revisions, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - 279 Church St. - closing documents, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - 279 Church St. - insurance documentation, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Unsigned lease w/ annotations, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence w/ landlord Madeline Droege [incl. lease info, other legal documents, violations, etc.], 2004 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence w/ landlord Madeline Droege [incl. lease info, other legal documents, violations, etc.], 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence w/ landlord Madeline Droege [incl. lease info, other legal documents, violations, etc.], 2004-2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence w/ landlord Madeline Droege [incl. lease info, other legal documents, violations, etc.], 2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 279 Church St. building/theater - misc legal, financial, and logistical files, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Clothing catalogs, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - C:U newsletter/donation solicitation, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Employee benefit information, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - First aid, fireguard inspection checklists, and F94 ID cards, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Letterhead, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Member code of conduct, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Business cards and telephone numbers, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - E-mail list and C:U retreat info, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - E-mail list, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - E-mail/phone list, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Misc. adresses, e-mail/phone lists [orig. "add to mailing list"], undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Misc. phone lists, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Phone messages, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Phone messages, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Phone messages, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Not-for-profit certificate, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - NYPR Star Initiative participation certificate, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Operating manuals for electronic devices, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Misc. pamphlets and show programs, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Scott's notes about 145 Ludlow St. lease problems, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Subseries B: Minutes
    - Meeting minutes, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Meeting agendas/minutes, 1997-2001 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Meeting agendas/minutes, 1997-2001 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Meeting agendas/minutes, 1997-2001 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Meeting minutes, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Meeting minutes, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Meeting minutes, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Subseries C: Financial
    - Receipts, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Guarantee receipt [blank], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Financial register, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Income/expense report, 1995-2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Teleplex payphone contract & receipts, 1995-2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bank account ledger, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Receipts, checks, and other misc. financial records, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Account info and pettry cash ledger, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Tax forms, Daniel E. Green, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Closed
    - Financial statements and account ledger, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Petty cash ledger, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Receipts, checks, and other misc. financial records, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 12)